8 It was long past noon when he awoke.
His valet had crept several times on tiptoe into the room to see if he was
stirring, and had wondered what made his young master sleep so late. Finally his
bell sounded, and Victor came in softly with a cup of tea, and a pile of letters,
on a small tray of old severis china, and drew back the olive satin curtains, with
their shimmering blue lining, that hung in front of the three tall windows
missure as well slept this morning,” he said, smiling.
“What o' is it, Victor?” asked Dorian Gray drowsily 1 hour and a quarter
mure How late it was! He sat up, and having sipped some tea, turned over his
letters. One of them was from Lord Henry, and had been brought by hand that
morning. He hesitated for a moment, and then put it aside. The others he opened
listlessly. They contained the usual collection of cards invitation ations to
dinner, tickets for private views programs of charity concerts, and the
like that are showered on fashionable young men every morning during the
season. There was a rather heavy bill for a chased silver Lou K's toilet set that
he had not yet had the courage to send on to his guardians, who were extremely
old-fashioned people and did not realize that we live in an age when unnecessary
things are our only necessities; and there were several very Court ious L
worded communications from German Street money lenders offering to advance any
sum of money at a moment’s notice and at the most reasonable rates of
interest. After about 10 minutes he got up, and throwing on an elaborate dressing
gown of silk embroidered cashmere wool, passed into the Onyx paved
bathroom. The cool water refreshed him after his long sleep. He seemed to have
forgotten all that he had gone through. A dim sense of having taken part
in some strange tra tragedy came to him once or twice, but there was the
unreality of a dream about it. As soon as he was dressed, he went into the library
and sat down to a light French breakfast that had been laid out for him on a
small round table close to the open window. It was an exquisite day. The warm
air seemed laden with spices. A bee flew in and buzzed around the Blue Dragon
bowl that, filled with sulfur yellow roses, stood before him. He felt perfectly happy.
Suddenly his eye fell on the screen that he had placed in front of the portrait, and he
started. “Too cold for mure asked his valet, putting an omelet on the table. “I shut the
window?” Dorian shook his head I'm not cold,” he murmured. Was it all true? Had the
portrait really changed? Or had it been simply his own imagination that had made
him see a look of evil where there had been a look of
joy? Surely a pain Ed canvas could not alter? The thing was absurd. It would
serve as a tale to tell Basil someday It would make him
smile. And, yet, how vivid was his recollection of the whole thing! First in
the dim twilight, and then in the bright dawn, he had seen the touch of cruelty
around the warped lips. He almost dreaded his valet leaving the room. He knew that
when he was alone he would have to examine the portrait. He was afraid of
certainty. When the coffee and cigarettes had been brought and the man turned to
go, he felt a wild desire to tell him to remain. As the door was closing behind
him, he called him back. The man stood waiting for his orders. Dorian looked at
him for a moment I'm not at home to anyone Victor,” he said with a sigh. The
man bowed and retired. Then he rose from the table, lit
a cigarette, and flung himself down on a luxurious curiously cushioned couch that
stood facing the screen. The screen was an old one, of guilt Spanish leather, stamped and
wrought with a rather flid Lou quator pattern. He scanned it curiously,
wondering if ever before it had concealed the secret of a man’s
life. Should he move it aside, after all?
Why not let it stay there? What was the use of knowing? If the thing was true, it
was terrible. If it was not true, why trouble about it? But what if, by some
fate or deadlier chance, eyes other than his spied behind and saw the horrible
change? What should he do if Basil hallwood came and asked to look at his
own picture? Basil would be sure to do that. No; the thing had to be examined, and
at once. Anything would be better than this dreadful state of doubt. He got up and locked both
doors. At least he would be alone when he looked upon the mask of his shame. Then
he drew the screen aside and saw himself face to face. It was perfectly true. The portrait had
altered. As he often remembered afterwards, and always with no small
wonder, he found himself at first gazing at the portrait with a feeling of almost scientific
interest. That such a change should have taken place was incredible to him. And
yet it was a fact Act Was there some subtle affinity between the chemical
atoms that shaped themselves into form and color on the canvas and the soul that was within
him? Could it be that what the soul thought, they realized?— ?—that what it dreamed, they made
true? Or was there some other, more terrible reason? He shuddered, and felt
afraid, and, going back to the couch, lay there, gazing at the picture in sickened
horror. One thing, however, he felt that it had done for him. It had made him
conscious how unjust, how cruel, he had been to cibil Vain It was not too late
to make reparation for that. She could still be his wife. His unreal and selfish
love would yield to some higher influence, would be transformed into some
nobler passion, and the portrait that Basil holwood had painted of him would
be a guide to him through life, would be to him what holiness is to some, and
conscience to others, and the fear of God to us all. There were opiates for remorse,
drugs that could lull the moral sense to sleep. But here was a visible symbol of
the degradation of sin. Here was an everpresent sign of the ruin men brought upon their
souls 3:00 struck, and four, and the half hour rang its double chime, but Dorian
Gray did not stir. He was trying to gather up the scarlet threads of life and to weave
them into a pattern; to find his way through the sanguine labyrinth of
passion through which he was wandering. He did not know what to do, or what to
think. Finally, he went over to the table and wrote a passionate letter to the
girl he had loved, imploring her forgiveness and accusing himself of
madness. He covered page after page with wild words of sorrow and wilder words of
pain. There is a luxury in self- reproach When we blame ourselves, we feel that no
one else has a right to blame us. It is the confession, not the priest, that gives us
absolution. When Dorian had finished the letter, he felt that he had been
forgiven. Suddenly there came a knock to the door, and he heard Lord Henry’s voice
outside. “My dear boy, I must see you. Let
me in at once. I can’t bear you shutting yourself up like
this.” He made no answer at first, but remained quite still. The knock King
still continued and grew louder. Yes, it was better to let Lord
Henry in, and to explain to him the new life he was going to lead, to quarrel
with him if it became necessary to quarrel, to part if parting was
inevitable. He jumped up, drew the screen hastily across the picture, and unlocked the
door I'm so sorry for it all, Dorian,” said Lord Henry as he entered. “But you must
not think too much about it.” “Do you mean about cibil V asked the
lad. “Yes, of course,” answered Lord Henry, sinking into a chair and slowly pulling
off his yellow gloves. “It is dreadful, from one point of view, but it was not
your fault. Tell me, did you go behind and see her, after the play was over?” “Yes.” “I
felt sure you had. Did you make a scene with her?” “I was brutal, Harry— —perfectly
brutal. But it is all right now I'm not sorry for anything that has happened
happed It has taught me to know myself better adorian I'm so glad you take it
in that way! I was afraid I would find you plunged in remorse and tearing that
nice curly hair of yours I've got through all that,” said Dorian, shaking his
head and smiling I'm perfectly happy now.
I know what conscience is, to begin with.
It is not what you told me it was. It is
the divinest thing in us. Don’t sneer at it, Harry anymore at least not before me.
I want to be good. I can’t bear the idea of my soul being
hideous.” “A very charming artistic basis for ethics, Dorian! I congratulate you on
it. But how are you going to begin?” “By marrying cibil vain Marrying cibil vain cried Lord
Henry, standing up and looking at him in perplexed amazement. “But, my dear Dorian—”
“Yes, Harry, I know what you are going to say. Something dreadful about marriage.
Don’t say it. Don’t ever say things of
that kind to me again 2 days ago I asked
cble to marry me I'm not going to break my word to her. She is to be my
wife.” “Your wife! Dorian! Didn’t you get my letter? I wrote to you this morning, and
sent the note down by my own man.” “Your letter? Oh, yes, I remember. I have not read
it yet, Harry. I was afraid there might be something in it that I wouldn’t like. You
cut life to pieces with your epigrams.” “You know nothing then?” “What do
you mean?” Lord Henry walked across the room, and sitting down by Dorian Gray,
took both his hands in his own and held them tightly. “Dorian,” he said, “my letter—
—don’t be frightened— —was to tell you that cibil vain is dead.” A cry of pain broke
from the lad’s lips, and he leaped to his feet, tearing his hands away from Lord
Henry’s grasp. “Dead cibil dead! It is not true! It is a horrible lie! How dare you
say it say It is quite true, Dorian,” said Lord Henry, gravely. “It is in all the morning
papers. I wrote down to you to ask you not to see anyone till I came. There will
have to be an inquest, of course, and you must not be mixed up in it. Things like
that make a man fashionable in Paris.
But in London people are so prejudiced. Here, one should never make
one’s debut with a scandal. One should reserve that to give an interest to one’s old
age. I suppose they don’t know your name at the theater If they don’t it's all
right. Did anyone see you going round to her room? That is an important point.”
Dorian did not answer for a few moments.
He was dazed with horror. Finally he stammered, in a stifled voice, “Harry, did
you say an inquest? What did you mean by
that? Did Cil Oh, Harry, I can’t bear it!
But be quick. Tell me everything at once.” “I have no doubt it was not an
accident, Dorian, though it must be put in that way to the public. It seems that as
she was leaving the theater with her mother, about half 12 or so, she said she
had forgotten something upstairs. They waited some time for her,
but she did not come down again. They ultimately found her lying dead on the
floor of her dressing room She had swallowed something by mistake, some
dreadful thing they use at theaters I don’t know what it was, but it had either
prussic acid or white lead in it. I should fancy it was pric acid, as she
seems to have died instantaneously.” “Harry, Harry, it is terrible!” cried the
lad. “Yes; it is very tragic, of course, but you must not get yourself mixed up in it.
I see by The Standard that she was 17 I should have thought she was almost
younger than that. She looks such a child, and seemed to know so little about acting.
Dorian, you mustn’t let this thing get on your nerves. You must come and dine with
me, and afterwards we will look in at the opera. It is a Patty night, and everybody
will be there. You can come to my sister’s box she's got some smart women with
her.” “So I have murdered Cil vain said Dorian Gray, half to himself, “murdered her
as surely as if I'd cut her little throat with a knife. Yet the roses are
not less lovely for all that. The birds sing just as happily in my garden. And
tonight I am to dine with you, and then go on to the opera, and Su somewhere, I
suppose, afterwards. How extraordinarily dramatic life is! If I had read all this
in a book, Harry, I think I would have wept over it. Somehow, now that it has
happened actually, and to me, it seems far too wonderful for
tears. Here is the first passionate love letter I have ever written in my life.
Strange, that my first passionate love letter should have been addressed to a
dead girl. Can they feel, I wonder, those white silent people we call the dead
syil Can she feel, or know, or listen? Oh, Harry, how I loved her once! It seems
years ago to me now. She was everything to me. Then came that dreadful night— —was
it really only last night?— ?—when she played so badly, and my heart almost
broke. She explained it all to me. It was terribly pathetic. But I was not moved a
bit. I thought her shallow. Suddenly something happened that made me
afraid. I can’t tell you what it was, but
it was terrible. I said I would go back to her. I felt I had done wrong.
And now she's dead. My God! My God! Harry, what shall I do?
You don’t know the danger I am in, and there is nothing to keep me straight. She
would have done that for me. She had no right to kill herself. It was selfish of
her.” “My dear Dorian,” answered Lord Henry, taking a cigarette from his case and
producing a gold Latin matchbox, “the only way a woman can ever
reform a man is by boring him so completely that he loses all possible
interest in life. If you had married this girl, you would have been wretched. Of
course, you would have treated her kindly.
One can always be kind to people about whom one cares nothing. But she would have soon found
out that you were absolutely indifferent to her. And when a woman finds that out
about her husband, she either becomes dreadfully dowy or wears very smart
bonnets that some other woman’s husband has to pay for I I say nothing about the
social mistake, which would have been abject— —which, of course, I would not have
allowed— —but I assure you that in any case the whole thing would have been an absolute
failure.” “I suppose it would,” muttered the lad, walking up and down the room and
looking horribly pale. “But I thought it was my duty. It is not my fault that this
terrible tragedy has prevented my doing what was right. I remember your saying once that
there is a fatality about good resolution s that they are always made
too late. Mine certainly were.” “Good resolutions are useless attempts to
interfere with scientific laws. Their origin is pure vanity. Their result is
absolutely nil They give us, now and then, some of those luxurious sterile emotions
that have a certain charm for the weak.
That is all that can be said for them.
They are simply checks that men draw on a bank where they have no account.” “Harry,”
cried Dorian Gray, coming over and sitting down beside him, “why is it that I
cannot feel this tragedy as much as I want to? I don’t think I'm heartless. Do
you?” “You have done too many foolish things during the last fortnite to be
entitled to give yourself that name, Dorian,” answered Lord Henry with his sweet melancholy
smile. The lad frowned. “I don’t like that explanation, Harry,” he rejoined, “but I am glad you
don’t think I am heartless. I am nothing
of the kind. I know I am not. And yet I must admit that this thing that has
happened does not affect me as it should. It seems to me to be simply like
a wonderful ending to a wonderful play. It has all the terrible beauty of a
Greek tragedy, a tragedy in which I took a great part, but by which I have not been
wounded.” “It is an interesting question,” said Lord Henry, who found an exquisite
pleasure in playing on the lad’s unconscious egotism, “an extremely interesting
question. I fancy that the true explanation is this: It often happens that the real
tragedies of life occur in such an inartistic manner that they hurt us by
their crude violence, their absolute incoherence, their absurd want of meaning,
their entire lack of style. They affect us just as vulgarity
affects us. They give us an impression of sheer brute force, and we revolt against
that. Sometimes, however, a tragedy that possesses artistic elements of beauty
crosses our lives. If these elements of beauty are real, the whole thing simply
appeals to our sense of dramatic effect.
Suddenly we find that we are no longer the actors, but the spectators of the
play. Or rather we are both. We watch ourselves, and the mere one th of the
spectacle enthralls us. In the present case, what is it that has really
happened someone has killed herself for love of you. I wish that I had ever had such an
experience. It would have made me in love with love for the rest of my life. The
people who have adored me— —there have not been very many, but
there have been some— —have always insisted on living on, long after I had
ceased to care for them, or they to care for me. They have become stout and
tedious, and when I meet them, they go in at once for reminiscences. That awful memory of woman!
What a fearful thing it is! And what an utter intellectual stagnation it reveals!
One should absorb the color of life, but one should never remember its details.
Details are always vulgar.” “I must sew poppies in my garden,” sighed
Dorian. “There is no necessity,” rejoined his companion. “Life has always poppies in
her her hands. Of course, now and then things linger. I once wore nothing but
violets all through one season, as a form of artistic mourning for a romance that would not
die. Ultimately, however, it did die. I forget what killed it. I think it
was her proposing to sacrifice the whole world for me. That is always a dreadful
moment. It fills one with the terror of eternity. Well— —would you believe it?—
?—a week ago, at Lady Hampshire’s, I found myself seated at dinner next to the lady
in question, and she insisted on going over the whole thing again, and digging
up the past, and raking up the future. I had buried my romance in a bed of
asphodel. She dragged it out again and assured me that I had spoiled her life
I'm bound to state that she ate an enormous dinner, so I did not feel any
anxiety. But what a lack of taste she showed!
The one charm of the past is that it is the past. But women never know when the
curtain has fallen. They always want a sixth act, and
as soon as the interest of the play is entirely over, they propose to continue
it. If they were allowed their own way, every comedy would have a tragic ending,
and every tragedy would culminate in a farce. They are charmingly artificial, but
they have no sense of art. You are more fortunate than I am. I assure you Dory
that not one of the women I have known would have done for me what cibil V did
for you. Ordinary women always console themselves. Some of them do it by going
in for sentimental colors Never trust a woman who wears mave whatever her age
may be, or a woman over 35 who is fond of pink ribbons. It always means that they
have a history. Others find a great consolation in suddenly discovering the
good qualities of their husbands. They flaunt their conjugal
felicity in one face, as if it were the most fascinating of sins. Religion consoles
some. Its mysteries have all the charm of a flirtation, a woman once told me, and I
can quite understand it. Besides, nothing makes one so vain as being told that one
is a sinner. Conscience makes egotists of us all. Yes; there is really no end to the
consolations that women find in modern life. Indeed, I have not mentioned the most important
one.” “What is that, Harry?” said the lad listlessly. “Oh, the obvious consolation.
Taking someone else’s admirer when one loses one’s own. In good society that
always whitewashes a woman. But really, Dorian, how different Cil van must have
been from all the women one meets! There is something to me quite beautiful about her
death I'm glad I'm living in a century when such wonders happen. They make one
believe in the reality of the things we all play with, such romance, passion, and
love.” “I was terribly cruel to her. You forget that I'm afraid that women appreciate
cruelty, downright cruelty, more than anything else. They have wonderfully
primitive instincts. We have emancipated them, but they remain slaves looking for
their masters, all the same. They love being dominated I'm sure you were
splendid I've never seen you really and absolutely angry, but I can fancy how
delightful you looked. And, after all, you said something to me the day before
yesterday that seemed to me at the time to be merely fanciful, but that I see now
was absolutely true, and it holds the key to everything.” “What was that, Harry?” “You said
to me that cibil van represented to you all the heroins of romance— —that she was
Desdemona one night, and ofilia the other; that if she died as Juliet, she came to
life as imagin She will never come to life again now,”
muttered the lad, burying his face in his hands.
“No, she will never come to life. She has played her last part. But you must think
of that lonely death in the Torre dressing room simply as a strange lurid
fragment from some jacoban tragedy, as a wonderful scene from Webster, or Ford, or
sirel toer The girl never really lived, and so she has never really died. To you
at least she was always a dream, a phantom that flitted through
Shakespeare’s plays and left them lovelier for its presence, a read through
which Shakespeare’s music sounded richer and more full of joy. The moment she
touched actual life, she marred it, and it marred her, and so she passed away. Mourn
for ailia if you like. Put ashes on your head because Cordelia was
strangled. Cry out against Heaven because the daughter of Brabantio died. But don’t
waste your tears over Cil vain She was less real than they are.” There was a
silence. The evening darkened in the room.
Noiselessly, and with silver feet, the shadows crept in from the
garden. The colors faded wearily out of things. After some time Dorian Gray looked
up. “You have explained me to myself, Harry,” he murmured with something of a sigh of
relief. “I felt all that you have said, but somehow I was afraid of it, and I could
not express it to myself. How well you know me! But we will
not talk again of what has happened. It has been a marvelous experience. That is
all. I wonder if life has still in store for me anything as marvelous Life has
everything in store for you, Dorian. There is nothing that you, with your
extraordinary good looks, will not be able to do.” “But suppose, Harry, I became
haggard, and old, and wrinkled? What then?” “Ah, then,” said Lord Henry, rising to
go, “then, my dear Dorian, you would have to fight for your victories. As it is, they
are brought to you. No, you must keep your good looks. We live in an age that reads
too much to be wise, and that thinks too much to be beautiful. We cannot spare you.
And now you had better dress and drive down to the CL club. We are rather late,
as it is.” “I think I shall join you at the opera,
Harry. I feel too tired to eat anything.
What is the number of your sister’s box 27 I believe. It is on the grand tier.
You will see her name on the door. But I'm sorry you won’t come and dine.” “I
don’t feel up to it,” said Dorian listlessly. “But I'm awfully obliged to
you for all that you have said to me. You are certainly my best friend. No one has
ever understood me as you have.” “We are only at the beginning of our
friendship, Dorian,” answered Lord Henry, shaking him by the hand goodbye I shall
see you before 9:30 I hope. Remember Patty is singing.” As he closed the door behind him,
Dorian Gray touched the bell, and in a few minutes Victor appeared with the
lamps and drew the blinds down. He waited impatiently for him to go. The man seemed
to take an interminable time over everything. As soon as he had left, he
rushed to the screen and drew it back. No; there was no further change in the
picture. It had received the news of cibil Vain's death before he had known
of it himself. It was conscious of the events of life as they occurred. The
vicious cruelty that marred the fine lines of the mouth had, no doubt, appeared
at the very moment that the girl had drunk the poison, whatever it was.
Or was it indifferent to results? Did it merely take cognizance of
what passed within the soul? He wondered, and hoped that someday he would see the
change taking place before his very eyes, shuddering as he hoped
it. Poor cibil What a romance it had all been! She had often mimicked death on the
stage. Then Death himself had touched her and taken her with him. How had she
played that dreadful last scene?
Had she cursed him, as she died? No; she had died for love of him, and love would
always be a sacrament to him now. She had atoned for everything by the sacrifice
she had made of her life. He would not think anymore of what she had made him
go through, on that horrible night at the theater When he thought of her, it would
be as a wonderful tragic figure sent onto the world stage to show the supreme
reality of love. A wonderful tragic figure? Tears came to his eyes as he
remembered her childlike look, and winsome fanciful ways, and shy tremulous
grace. He brushed them away hastily and looked again at the
picture. He felt that the time had really come for making his
choice. Or had his choice already been made? Yes, life had decided that for him—
—life, and his own infinite curiosity about life. Eternal youth, infinite
passion, pleasures subtle and secret, wild joys and wilder sins— —he was to have all
these things. The portrait was to bear the burden of his shame: that was
all. A feeling of pain crept over him as he thought of the desecration that was
in store for the fair face on the canvas. Once, in boyish mockery of
Narcissus, he had kissed, or Fain to kiss, those painted lips that now smiled so cruy at
him. Morning after morning he had sat before the portrait wondering at its
beauty, almost enamored of it, as it seemed to him at times. Was it to alter
now with every mood to which he yielded?
Was it to become a monstrous and loome thing, to be hidden away in a locked room,
to be shut out from the sunlight that had so often touched a brighter gold the
waving wonder of its hair? The pity of it!
the pity of it! For a moment, he thought of praying that the horrible sympathy
that existed between him and the picture might cease. It had changed in answer to a
prayer; perhaps in answer to a prayer it might remain
unchanged. And yet, who, that knew anything about life, would surrender the chance of
remaining always young, however fantastic that chance might be, or with what
fateful consequences it might be fraught? Besides, was it really under his
control? Had it indeed been prayer that had produced the substitution? Might there not be some
curious scientific reason for it all? If thought could exercise its influence
upon a living organism, might not thought exercise an influence upon dead and
inorganic things? Nay, without thought or conscious desire, might not things
external to ourselves vibrate in unison with our moods and passions, atom calling
to atom in secret love or strange affinity? But the reason was of no
importance. He would never again tempt by a prayer any terrible
power. If the picture was to alter, it was to alter. That was
all. Why inquire too closely into it? For there would be a real pleasure in
watching it. He would be able to follow his mind into its secret
places. This portrait would be to him the most magical of mirrors. As it had
revealed to him his own body, so it would reveal to him his own soul. And when
winter came upon it, he would still be standing where spring trembles on the
verge of summer. When the blood crept from its face, and left behind a palid
mask of chalk with Leen eyes, he would keep the glamour of boyhood. Not one
blossom of his loveliness would ever fade. Not one pulse of his life would
ever weaken. Like the gods of the Greeks, he would be strong, and and fleet, and
joyous. What did it matter what happened to the colored image on the canvas? He
would be safe. That was everything. He drew the screen back into
its former place in front of the picture, smiling as he did so, and passed into his
bedroom, where his valet was already waiting for him. An hour later he was at the opera,
and Lord Henry was leaning over his
chair. CHAPTER nine